1:Who's there?
2:No, who are you? Stop and identify yourself.
1:Long live the king!
2:Is that Barnardo?
1:Yes, it's me.
2:You've arrived right on time.
1:The clock just struck twelve. Go to bed, Francisco.
2:Thanks for relieving me. It's bitterly cold,
and I'm saddened.
1:Has anything happened during your guard?
2:Not a mouse stirring.
1:Well, good night.
2:Stop! Who's there?
3:Friends to this country. And servants to the Danish king.
2:Good night to you both.
1:Farewell, honest soldier. Who has relieved you?
3:Barnardo took my place. Good night.
4:Hello, Barnardo.
1:Hello. Is Horatio here too?
3:Kind of.
1:Welcome, Horatio. Welcome, good Marcellus.
3:Did you see that thing again tonight?
1:I have seen nothing.
4:Horatio says it's our imagination
And won't believe in
The horrible thing we've seen twice now.
4:That's why I begged him to come on our shift tonight
4:So that if the ghost comes
He can see what we see and speak to it.
3:Nonsense, it won't appear.
1:Then let us tell you again
The story you don't want to believe,
About what we've seen two nights now.
3:Well, let's hear Barnardo talk about this.
1:Last night,
1:When that star to the west of the North star
1:Had traveled across the sky to light up that part of heaven
Where it shines now, Marcellus and I,
at one o'clock a.m.--
4:Look, it's come again!
1:Looking just like the dead king.
4:You're well-educated. Speak to it, Horatio.
1:Doesn't it look like the king, Horatio?
3:Very much so. It terrifies me.
1:It wants us to speak to it.
Ask it something, Horatio.
3:What are you, that you walk out so late at night
Looking like you're dressed for battle
3:In the same way the dead king of Denmark
when he dressed for battle? By God, I order
you to speak.
4:It is offended.
Look, it's going away.
3:Stay! Speak, speak! I order you, speak!
4:It's gone and will not answer.
3:I swear to God, I would not believe this
If I had not seen it with my own eyes.
4:It's happened like this twice before, always at
this exact time. He goes by our post with a
warrior's walk.
3:I don't really know how to explain this,
But I have the general feeling
This means bad news for our country.
4:Alright, come close and somebody tell me
Why this strict schedule of guards
Has been employed.
4:And why so many bronze cannons are being manufactured, and so many weapons bought from abroad.
4:Is there something about to happen that makes it necessary to work night and day?
4:Who can explain this to me?
3:I can. At least, these are the rumors: our late king,
3:Who we just saw now as a ghost, was a great rival or Fortinbras of Norway.
3:Fortinbras dared him to battle. In that fight, our courageous Hamlet killed Fortinbras, who surrendered all his territories, along with his life.
3:But now old Fortinbras' young son, also called Fortinbras, who is bold but unproven,
3:Has gathered up a bunch of lawless thugs from the outskirts of the country.
3:They're supposed to recover from us the the lands I mentioned that old Fortinbras lost. And this, I take it,
3:Is the main reason for our preparations, the reason for our posted here, and the chief reason
3:For the commotion in Denmark lately.
3:Wait, look! It has come again.
I'll cross it if it's the last thing I do. Stay, ghost!
3:If you have a voice or can make sounds, speak to me.
3:If you have some secret knowledge of our country's fate, which could be avoided if we knew about it, then please speak.
0:(cock crowing)
3:Stay and speak!
3:Keep it from leaving, Marcellus.
4:Should I strike it with my spear?
1:It's over here.
3:There it is.
4:It's gone. We were wrong to threaten it with violence, since it looks so much like a king.
4:Besides, we can't hurt it anymore than we can hurt the air. Our futile attack was just malicious mockery.
1:It was about to say something when the rooster crowed.
3:And then it acted startled, like a guilty person receiving a fearful summons.
4:Yes, it faded away when the rooster crowed.
Some say that just before Christmas
4:the rooster crows all night long
4:so that no ghost dares go wandering, and the night is safe. The planets have no effect on us,
4:fairies' spells don't work, and witches can't charm us, so holy that night is.
3:I've heard the same thing and kind of believe it.
3:But look, morning is appearing beyond that hill in the east, turning the sky red.
3:Let's stop our watch and go tell everything we've seen tonight
3:to young Hamlet. I bet my life that the ghost which is mute with us will speak to him.