1:Who's there?
2:Nay, answer me. Stand and unfold yourself.
1:Long live the king!
2:Barnardo?
1:He.
2:You come most carefully upon your hour.
1:'Tis now struck twelve. Get thee to bed, Francisco.
2:For this relief much thanks. 'Tis bitter cold,
And I am sick at heart.
1:Have you had quiet guard?
2:Not a mouse stirring.
1:Well, good night.
2:Stand, ho! Who's there?
3:Friends to this ground. And liegemen to the Dane.
2:Give you good night.
4:Farewell, honest soldier. Who hath relieved you?
2:Barnardo has my place. Give you good night.
4:Holla, Barnardo.
1:Say what, is Horatio there?
3:A piece of him.
1:Welcome, Horatio. Welcome, good Marcellus.
3:What, has this thing appeared again tonight?
1:I have seen nothing.
4:Horatio says 'tis but our fantasy
And will not let belief take hold of him
Touching this dreaded sight twice seen of us.
4:Therefore I have entreated him along
With us to watch the minutes of this night,
4:That if again this apparition come
He may approve our eyes and speak to it.
3:Tush, tush, 'twill not appear.
1:Then let us once again assail your ears,
That are so fortified against our story,
What we have two nights seen.
3:Well, let us hear Barnardo speak of this.
1:Last night of all,
When yond same star that's westward from the pole
1:Had made his course t' illume that part of heaven
Where it now burns, Marcellus and myself,
The bell then beating once--
4:Look where it comes again!
1:In the same figure like the king that's dead.
4:Thou art a scholar. Speak to it, Horatio.
1:Looks it not like the king? Mark it, Horatio.
3:Most like. It harrows me with fear and wonder.
1:It would be spoke to.
Question it, Horatio.
3:What art thou that usurp'st this time of night
Together with that fair and warlike form
3:In which the majesty of buried Denmark
Did sometimes march? By heaven, I charge thee,
speak.
4:It is offended.
See, it stalks away.
3:Stay! Speak, speak! I charge thee, speak!
4:'Tis gone and will not answer.
3:Before my God, I might not this believe
Without the sensible and true avouch
Of mine own eyes.
4:Thus twice before, and jump at this dead hour,
With martial stalk hath he gone by our watch.
3:In what particular thought to work I know not,
But in the gross and scope of mine opinion
This bodes some strange eruption to our state.
4:Good now, stand close, and tell me, he that knows,
Why this same strict and most observant watch
So nightly toils the subject of the land,
4:And why such daily cast of brazen cannon
And foreign mart for implements of war,
4:What might be toward, that this sweaty haste
Doth make the night joint laborer with the day?
4:Who is 't that can inform me?
3:That can I.
At least the whisper goes so: our last king,
3:Whose image even but now appeared to us,
Was, as you know, by Fortinbras of Norway,
3:Dared to the combat; in which our valiant Hamlet
Did slay this Fortinbras, who thus
Did forfeit, with his life, all these his lands.
3:Now, sir, young Fortinbras,
Of unimprovèd mettle hot and full,
3:Hath in the skirts of Norway here and there
Sharked up a list of lawless resolutes,
3:To recover of us, those foresaid lands
So by his father lost. And this, I take it,
3:Is the main motive of our preparations,
The source of this our watch, and the chief head
3:Of this posthaste and rummage in the land.
3:But soft, behold! Lo, where it comes again.
I'll cross it though it blast me. Stay, illusion!
3:If thou hast any sound or use of voice,
Speak to me.
3:If thou art privy to thy country's fate,
Which happily foreknowing may avoid,
Oh, speak!
0:(cock crowing)
3:Stay and speak!
3:Stop it, Marcellus.
4:Shall I strike at it with my partisan?
1:'Tis here.
3:'Tis here.
4:'Tis gone.
We do it wrong, being so majestical,
To offer it the show of violence,
4:For it is, as the air, invulnerable,
And our vain blows malicious mockery.
1:It was about to speak when the cock crew.
3:And then it started like a guilty thing
Upon a fearful summons.
3:It faded on the crowing of the cock.
Some say that ever 'gainst that season comes
3:Wherein our Saviour's birth is celebrated,
The bird of dawning singeth all night long.
4:And then, they say, no spirit dare stir abroad.
The nights are wholesome. Then no planets strike,
4:No fairy takes, nor witch hath power to charm,
So hallowed and so gracious is that time.
3:So have I heard and do in part believe it.
3:But look, the morn, in russet mantle clad,
Walks o'er the dew of yon high eastward hill.
3:Break we our watch up, and by my advice,
Let us impart what we have seen tonight
3:Unto young Hamlet, for, upon my life,
This spirit, dumb to us, will speak to him.